.
>> good afternoon.
Welcome to the MARCH 11th, 2025
regular meeting of the san
francisco board of supervisors
.
>> MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll?
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chen chan PRESIDENT
Supervisor chen chen present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
present supervisor and engardio
and engardio PRESIDENT
Supervisor fielder fielder
present supervisor mahmood
mahmood present supervisor
mandolin PRESIDENT Mandolin and
present supervisor melgar
melgar PRESIDENT Supervisor
sartor sadr present supervisor
sherril sherrell present and
supervisor walton walton
present.
>> MR. PRESIDENT all members
are present.
Thank you MADAM Clerk.
>> the san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges that
we are on the unceded ancestral
homeland of the dramatist aloni
who are the original
inhabitants of the san
francisco peninsula.
As the indigenous stewards of
this land and in accordance
with their traditions the
romita and maloney have never
ceded lost nor forgotten their
responsibilities as caretakers
of this place.
As well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory as guests we
recognize that we benefit from
living and working on their
traditional home land.
we wish to pay our respects by
acknowledging the ancestors,
elders and relatives of the
romita aloni community and by
affirming their sovereign
rights as first peoples.
Colleagues, will you join me
in reciting the pledge of
allegiance?
I pledge allegiance to the flag
of the united states of america
and to the republic for which
it stands one nation under GOD,
indivisible with liberty and
justice for all.
>> on behalf of the board I
want to acknowledge the staff
at S.F. Gov tv and today
particularly kaleena mendoza
who record each of our meetings
and make transcripts available
to the public online.
And with that, MADAM Clerk can
you take us to our 2 P.M.
Special order the mayor's
appearance?
Yes.
The special order at 2 P.M. Is
the appearance at today's
meeting by the honorable mayor
daniel lurie present to engage
in a formal policy discussion
with eligible board members
prior to the discussion the
mayor MAY address the board for
up to five minutes.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk and
welcome MR. Mayor.
>> mayor larry do you have any
opening remarks?
Thank you.
Good afternoon.
>> PRESIDENT Randleman and
members of the board this week
I am sending senior leaders of
our administration alongside
our city attorney david chiu to
join san francisco chamber of
commerce and top business
leaders to lobby our federal
for critical resources for san
francisco.
While I am prepared to make the
tough decisions to tackle the
city's budget crisis, we are
looking to washington to
partner with us on san
francisco's comeback.
With federal support we can
supercharge our economic
recovery by investing in a bold
vision for a hunter's point
naval shipyard and candlestick
point and upgrading our
critical transportation
infrastructure.
But as we advocate for those
resources, we are fighting
proposed cuts to essential
programs like food that provide
food, housing and health care
for hundreds of thousands of
san franciscans as well as fema
reimbursements for critical
work done to protect vulnerable
communities during covid.
San francisco drives and
innovation across the country.
And when san francisco wins the
country wins.
I'm grateful to senator
padilla, senator schiff and our
congressional delegation for
their support and to the san
francisco chamber of commerce
for their leadership on this
trip.
Our administration will
continue to stand with them and
leaders across san francisco to
protect the services our
residents depend on and invest
in our city's bright future.
Thank you and thank you, MR.
Mayor.
>> MADAM Clerk, could you
please call the topic?
>> yes.
The first topic submitted by
the district nine supervisor
supervisor fielder is
displacement effects into the
mission and the comprehensive
strategy to address the drug
crisis.
>> supervisor fielder.
You MAY ask your opening
question.
>> thank you, PRESIDENT And
thank you for coming and
answering this question.
You and I have been talking
about conditions along mission
street and the bart plazas
since our first sit down
in DECEMBER.
And you even came to 16th
street to going to walk with me
the dpw director mission
station please captain to see
the conditions for yourself.
And you've been many times
since.
I really appreciate your
partnership and consistency
in addressing challenges around
16th and mission.
And your ongoing participation
in community engagement in the
mission.
However, the recent enforcement
operations at sixth street have
displaced people across the
city including two 16th
in mission.
>> and the fentanyl crisis
persists regarding public drug
use and our addiction crisis.
>> how is your administration
defining the success of these
enforcement actions?
>> and do you think they've
been successful?
I appreciate the question,
supervisor fielder and I
appreciate our multiple walks
including the one at 16th and
mission.
And you're correct I've been
back many times and I was there
again last night for my
administration.
Success is measured by the
experiences our residents and
visitors feel.
It means a family walking down
16th and mission feel safe.
It means clean, well-maintained
sidewalks like those we saw
in front of the mission cabins.
Success is small business
owners feeling confident that
they can build and run their
businesses day and night.
And success means alleys like
white street in the mission are
free of trash and drug use.
>> my administration will
continue to make this message
clear through our enforcement
actions.
If you are dealing drugs we are
going to continue coming after
you.
We have carried out effective
interagency operations
targeting open air drug markets
and jefferson's square park and
on 16th and mission both times
we have removed dealers
paraphernalia and trash from
public spaces.
And the response in both
communities has been
overwhelmingly positive.
These operations are just one
component of our broader
strategy to get those
struggling with addiction into
the treatment they need.
Another critical component is
adding the necessary bed
capacity so we have options to
offer people on the streets to
move inside.
And I appreciate the board's
partnership in that work.
But these operations do help
send a clear message whether
in the tenderloin jefferson
square park, sixth street, 16th
in mission or anywhere in our
city, drug dealers will find no
safe harbor.
>> thank you.
I wholeheartedly agree that
street conditions perceptions
of safety have to be a part of
measuring success and at the
same time if you go out to 60
the mission and the alleyways
right now you'll largely see
more of the same.
And I understand that change
doesn't happen overnight.
>> but it's clear to me that
with enforcement alone without
a more comprehensive approach
and broader metrics for success
such as connecting people to
treatment on demand shelter
recovery programs, we're going
to continue to displace people
and public drug activities from
block to block and neighborhood
to neighborhood.
And that's why I've called for
a hearing on the four pillars
strategy strategy that our own
budget and legislative
analyst's office has
recommended and has been tested
as an evidence based approach
that equally prioritizes
prevention slash education harm
reduction and treatment
alongside enforcement.
And I think supervisors dorsey
walton chan and mahmood for
co-sponsor in this hearing
zurich, switzerland was ones
facing similar poor street
conditions addiction and
overdose rates as we are now
and it is now among the safest
cities in the world right now
it seems your administration's
strategy is leading heavily
with enforcement.
>> so I want to know if your
administration would commit to
equally prioritizing the other
pillars and these successful
four pillars model to provide a
unified strategy and a lasting
solution to our city's fentanyl
crisis.
As I was saying at the heart of
my administration, strategy for
improving conditions on the
streets are our efforts to help
people move into the treatment
and the care that they need.
To achieve this we must
strengthen and expand our
behavioral health and
homelessness systems.
That also means supporting
people to reach recovery both
when they are ready but also
when they need it most.
With our new department of
public health director dan sy
who started just last week, we
are working to add beds across
the continuum of care from
shelter to locked behavioral
health beds.
I appreciate the board of
supervisors and your support
for my fentanyl state of
emergency ordinance which is
helping us tackle this crisis
with the urgency it demands.
With its passage we will be
able to quickly open first
responder friendly treatment
sites like a22 garry and add
much needed treatment beds for
those struggling with severe
mental illness and addiction.
This legislation also allows us
to streamline procurement of
these sites and hire essential
public health workers and where
necessary law enforcement to
strengthen our response
alongside our enforcement work
to stop the sale of deadly
fentanyl in our streets.
we are also providing services
to people who are on the
pathway to recovery who MAY not
be sure what type of support
they need.
And we are helping them steer
them towards treatment.
For my administration, success
means helping people regain
their health and stability but
also for our entire community
to feel safer in san francisco.
I look forward to collaborating
with you supervisor and all of
your colleagues on a long term
sustainable approach to address
our city's fentanyl crisis.
Thank you so much.
>> thank you mayor lori.
You MAY now ask a question to
supervisor fielder or to any
other supervisor in attendance
pertaining to the same topic
but not necessarily related to
the previous question.
I appreciate the opportunity
but I'm good.
Thank you PRESIDENT.
Thank you all very much for
having me today.
Thank you, MR. Mayor.
>> thank you very much.
Pleasure to be here.
You're out of order.
>> just all right, MADAM Clerk,
that concludes our mayoral
discussions and the matter has
been discussed and is now filed
.
>> and then we're going to go
back to our communications.
>> MADAM Clerk, are there any
communications?
Yes.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
The san francisco board of
supervisors welcomes your
attendance to this meeting
in the board's legislative
chamber room 250 within city
hall on the second floor.
If you can't make it down here,
you MAY watch the proceeding on
S.F. Govee tv's channel 26 or
even view the live stream at w
w w dot S.F. Geo vtv.Org.
You MAY also submit your public
comment by sending an email to
boss at S.F. Gov dot org or use
the postal service address your
envelope to the san francisco
board of supervisors.
The number one DR. Carlton b
good place city hall room 244
san francisco california 94102.
To make a reasonable
accommodation request under the
americans with disabilities act
or to request language
assistance, contact the clerk's
office at least two business
days in advance by calling
(415) 554-5184.
And finally, MR. PRESIDENT, my
office is in receipt of an ada
accommodation request to
provide public statements as
the first speaker during
general public comment.
At that time my staff and I
will make sure that this
individual gets submitted to
make remote comment as vetted
by the ada.
>> great.
Thank you MADAM Clerk.
>> let's go to approval of the
meeting minutes.
Approval of the FEBRUARY 4th
2025 board meeting minutes.
>> all right, colleagues.
>> as our clerk indicated,
we're approving the meeting
minutes from the FEBRUARY 4th,
2025 regular board meeting.
Are there any changes to these
meeting minutes?
I don't see any.
Can I have a motion to approve
the minutes as presented moved
by melgar.
Can I have a second seconded by
fielder.
And MADAM Clerk will you please
call the roll on the minutes as
presented supervisor melgar.
Melgar eyes supervisor sartor.
Sartor eyes supervisor sherril
sherril eyes supervisor walton
walton eyes supervisor chin
chin eyes supervisor chin chin
eyes supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and engardio and
engardio I supervisor fielder
fielder I supervisor mahmood
mohamud I and supervisor
mendelson hi mandolin I there
are 11 eyes.
>> without objection the
minutes will be approved after
public comment as presented
MADAM Clerk let's go to the
consent agenda items two
through eight items two through
eight are on consent.
These items are considered to
be routine.
If a member objects an item MAY
be removed and considered
separately.
>> colleagues does anyone want
to sever any items from the
consent agenda?
I don't see anyone MADAM Clerk
can you please call the roll on
items two through eight
supervisor melgar melgar eyes
supervisor sadr sadr eyes
supervisor sherril sherril eyes
supervisor walton walton eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor and engardio
engardio eyes supervisor
fielder hi fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I.
And supervisor mendelson hi
mendelson either are 11 eyes
without objection these
ordinances are finally passed
MADAM Clerk please call the
regular agenda unfinished
business item number nine item
nine this is an ordinance to
retroactively authorize the san
francisco public library to
accept and expend a $1.9
million grant from the andrew w
mellon foundation for the jail
and reentry services program
NOVEMBER 1st, 2024 through
DECEMBER 31st, 2027 and to
amend the annual salary
ordinance for fiscal years 2024
through 25 and 2025 through 26
to provide for the addition of
one grant funded full time
position in class 3630 a
librarian one grant funded full
time position in class 1822 an
admin analyst and a grant
funded full time position
in class 1823 a senior admin
analyst at the public library
through JUNE 30th 2020 six
MADAM Clerk, I think we can
take this item the same house
same call without objection the
ordinance is finally passed.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item number ten?
>> item ten this is an
ordinance to amend the campaign
and governmental conduct code
to update the conflicts of
interest codes form seven
hundred the filing requirements
by adding, deleting and
changing titles of certain
designated officials and
employees to reflect
organizational and staffing
changes and by refining
disclosure requirements for
certain designated officials
and employees.
And we can take this item same
house, same call without
objection.
this ordinance is finally
passed.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call
item number 11.
Item 11 this is an ordinance to
amend the administrative code
to authorize the tax collector
to refund property taxes to the
assessee or latest recorded
owner of the property if the
amount of the refund is less
than 10,000 and there has been
no transfer of the property
during or since the fiscal year
for which the taxes to be
refunded were levied and we can
take this item same house, same
call without objection this
ordinance is finally passed.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 12?
>> item 12 this is an ordinance
to amend the business and tax
regulations code to remove the
requirement that parking
operators certify and report
periodically to the city the
ratio of their unaccounted
parking tickets to total issued
tickets for each parking
station for the reporting
period.
>> and let's take this item
same house, same call.
Without objection this
ordinance is finally passed.
>> MADAM Clerk, let's go to our
new business.
>> can you call item number 13?
Item 13 this is an ordinance to
amend the business and tax
regulations code to authorize
the tax collector to waive
taxes, penalties and or
interest under a program ending
DECEMBER 31st, 2027 that allows
unregistered taxpayers to
voluntarily disclose and pay
back taxes and to authorize the
tax collector to collect fees
through DECEMBER 31st, 2027 for
reviewing applications for and
providing advanced
determinations to taxpayers.
>> I think we can take this
item same house, same call
without objection this
ordinance is passed on first
reading and MADAME Clerk, can
you please call item number 14
for item 14 in accordance with
section 2961 of article 29 a of
the business and tax
regulations code passage of
this ordinance by the board
requires an affirmative vote of
two thirds or eight votes of
the full membership.
Item 14 is an ordinance to
amend the business and tax
regulations code to suspend the
empty homes tax pending a final
decision in eric dubon at all
versus the city and to
reinstate that tax so that the
tax first applies in the tax
year immediately following the
calendar year of that final
decision.
>> supervisor fielder thank you
PRESIDENT Colleagues, I would
like to make a motion to
continue item 14.
After careful review and
consultation with the city
attorney, I would like to
explore amendments that would
potentially avoid having the
empty homes tax suspended for
years as the case makes its way
through the courts and instead
providing a pathway that would
allow the city to begin
collecting the tax once the
courts give us the green light
as the current legislation is
written we would be suspending
the empty homes tax until the
entire case is resolved whereas
the amendments I am exploring
would suspend the empty homes
tax only until the courts tell
us otherwise when the courts
allow us to implement the tax I
want to make sure that we are
not proactively limiting our
ability to collect the tax
until the final decision on all
appeals is lifted.
>> the intent of the homes tax
measure was to fill thousands
of empty homes across the city
that are being left off of the
market.
And my hope is that we can work
out some amendments that would
ensure the city is implementing
the tax as soon as the court
allows while also addressing
the concerns of the treasures
office to ensure we are
fulfilling the will of the
voters.
I would like to thank scott
reber, chief tax attorney for
taking our questions and the
treasurer's team for being open
to a continuance of this item
until our next board meeting.
>> thank you.
Supervisor fielder.
Supervisor fielder has made a
motion to continue this item
until the 18th.
Supervisor walton has seconded
that motion.
I think we can take that
colleagues without objection.
Without objection.
>> this item is continued until
MARCH 18th.
MADAM Clerk, can you call items
15 and 16 together?
>> item 15 is a resolution that
approves the second
modification to an airport
contract number 119 18.41
project management support
services for the sfo for san
francisco international airport
cargo building six 620 6.1
project with consider pmc m inc
with a contract increased by
10.3 million for a new total of
13 million and a four year
contract extension MAY 2nd 2024
through MAY 1st 2029.
And item 16 this resolution
approves a second modification
to an airport contract number
119 84.41 project management
support services for the sfo
cargo building seven 20.1 and
gsc building 742 project with
westfield consultants, a joint
venture between wsp usa inc and
agc inc to increase the
contract amount by 10 million
for a new total of 13 million
to extend the contract for
services an additional four
years through MAY 1st 2029 and
to make the appropriate
findings for both items.
>> let's take these items.
Same house, same call.
>> without objection these
resolutions are adopted.
>> MADAME Clerk, can you please
call item 17?
Item 17 this is a resolution
for real property a lease
amendment for communication and
control inc communications
services facilities in alameda
county for a monthly base rent
of $9,080.
>> let's take this item same
house, same call.
Without objection this
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk, please call item
number 18 item 18 this is a
resolution to approve an
emergency declaration of the
san francisco public utilities
commission to contract
resources to restore the tesla
treatment facilities.
Uninterruptible standby power
supplies system which has
become obsolete and was found
to have failed anderson for 11
2024 during routine maintenance
with the total estimated cost
of 700,000.
And we can take this item.
Same house, same call without
objection this resolution is
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call items 19 and 20 together?
>> items 19 and 20 are two
resolutions that approve and
authorize real property leases
for the real estate department.
Item 19 approves a property
lease with family and child
empowerment services for
approximately 3000ft2 for the
village community facility
located at 1099 sunnydale
avenue in san francisco for an
initial term of five years with
two five year options to extend
at an initial rent of
approximately 49,000 per year
with 3% annual increases
thereafter.
The initial rent will include
approximately 822ft2 of office
space in support of a temporary
grant and programing
collaboration with family
connections center to provide
services to the community
should future grants for said
collaboration not be funded
after the first year of the
lease or any subsequent year
thereafter during the initial
five year term, the new
adjusted rent will be
approximately 3000 per month or
approximately 36,000 per year
with a 3% annual increase.
Item 20 this resolution
approves and authorizes the
director of real property to
enter into a real property
lease with the felton
institute, a california
nonprofit public benefit
corporation for approximately
1500ft2 for the village
community facility located at
1099 sunnydale avenue for a
five year initial term with two
year options to extend at an
initial rent of approximately
24,000 per year 3% annual
increases thereafter and a
finding that competitive
bidding procedures required
under the administrative code
are impractical or impossible
and a finding that the lease
furthers a proper public
purpose sufficient to meet the
administrative code market
value requirements for both
matters MADAM Clerk that was a
mouthful.
It is moments like this when we
feel such appreciation for you
and your staff.
Thank you MADAM Clerk.
MR. PRESIDENT, I think we can
take these items same house,
same call without objection
these resolutions these
resolutions are adopted and
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call items number 21 and 22
together?
>> items 21 and 22 are two
resolutions that pertain to the
health service system contract
amendments item 21 approves a
third amendment to the
agreement between the city and
highland software inc for
software that facilitates
capture organization and
storage of sfh s member
documents to extend the term by
five years for a total term
JANUARY 4th, 2016 through MARCH
31st 2030 with a contract
increase of 200,000 for a new
total of 574,000.
>> item 22 this resolution
approves the 10th amendment to
an agreement between the city
and pinay administrative
services to administer cobra ab
528 programs health care
spending accounts and flexible
spending accounts to extend the
term by 18 months for a total
term of 12 years from MARCH
first 2015 through DECEMBER
31st, 2026 and a contract
increase of 555,000 for a new
total of 4.6 million.
>> and we could take these
items same house, same call
without objection these
resolutions are adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk let's go to roll
call.
First up to introduce new
business is supervisor melgar.
>> thank you so much MADAM
Clerk.
At colleagues at today I join
supervisors order a soon to be
parent who will speak right
after me.
>> in introducing a motion to
formalize a parental leave
policy for the board of
supervisors.
>> this effort believe or not
has taken decades and is still
an ongoing challenge.
>> former supervisor michela
alioto pier led the way by
having to navigate her own
pregnancy and parental leave as
an elected official.
She brought this issue to the
voters in 2000 and six through
a charter amendment to allow
for remote conferencing ability
for board members or
commissioners.
>> the charter had not assumed
that that was a possibility
before.
>> however, the brown act
required publicly disclosing
remote locations to utilize
this ability which means having
to disclose your home or public
hospital room making her public
in 2021 during women's history
month I introduce in the
board's subsequently passed an
ordinance to codify parts of
the charter amendment for
commissions and board because
prior to that commissioners did
not have this and it was
inconsistent.
We had had a couple of
commissioners who had
pregnancies in pregnancy and
parental leave after who had no
way of navigating that process.
At the same time we work with
some state legislators to
update the brown act with
parental leave pregnancy and
caregiving in mind so that the
remote voting and participation
could be more feasible.
Unfortunately many of those
efforts fell just short.
Fast forwarding to 2025, the
state legislature made
incremental progress by passing
a bill that allows some remote
attendance for just cause or
emergency circumstances for her
board members attending public
meetings.
And this just went into effect
in JANUARY.
As such, we need to formally
adopt a parental leave policy
for the board of supervisors
members to fully align with
these updates and to provide
the ability for members to take
official leave to bond with
their new children and to be
supported in that role.
>> we should be normalizing
taking official paid leave but
in the event that it is desired
,members should also have the
ability to participate fully
in these chambers remotely.
This is a step in the right
direction.
We're still very much limited
by the confines of the brown
act and we will continue
pushing the envelope with our
state legislature so that we
can continue advocating for
policies that are supportive of
and accessible for parents and
caregivers.
This movement is growing with
debate taking place at the
national stage.
We had senator tammy duckworth
from illinois being the first
person to serve while you know,
giving birth.
Recently U.S. Representative at
peterson of colorado was denied
the ability to vote remotely
despite being weeks from her
due date with her second
pregnancy.
Just two weeks ago she had to
bring her newborn baby to the
house floor to cast her vote to
oppose the ill conceived budget
deal.
Our democracy thrives when we
are able to see the
representatives in these seats
reflect everyday people and far
too long for far too long we
have made a challenging for
caregivers a role that often
falls on women to be able to
fulfill these roles.
>> the us remains one of the
few countries in the world
without any national paid
parental leave policy and
during the pandemic we saw how
many people women and
caregivers had to leave the
workforce because of a lack of
support in the system.
Elected bodies around the world
are pushing for official
policies for the member and we
follow the footsteps of great
britain, canada and even nearby
redwood city who did this
before us.
I now turn it over to
supervisor so
der who I am so
excited and look forward to
serving on on the board
continuing to move along with
more family friendly policies
and I also want to thank MADAM
Clerk for her work and her
staff's work in putting this
together.
Thank you so much.
And the rest I submit to you.
Oh thank you supervisor melgar
.
>> supervisor sartor thank you.
And I want to first recognize
my colleague supervisor melgar
for all of her hard work on
this.
I think we see that if no one
does anything nothing happens
and you push this forward.
So thank you.
And as supervisor melgar
shared, this has been a long
journey to get to this moment.
Many individuals, particularly
women push this forward.
The voters of this city want
this and the voters of this
city made that clear in 26 when
they passed with a 72% ratio.
The urging to to make policy
and to set leave.
So we are finally doing that
today and you know, in a in a
personal sense I am my wife and
I are set to welcome our
daughter into this world and
into san francisco in a few
weeks.
and so we are excited but it
brings back to mind, you know,
difficult conversations in the
past few years around if we
could start a family in this
city and serve this city and we
have chosen to try and do both.
But I think that a policy and
actually setting policy like
we're doing today would make it
easier for more people to make
that decision and have clarity
about what that path might look
like.
So I hope that we will pass
this quickly and I know that
our message and our policy here
today will make it more
possible for more parents and
parents to be to serve our
great city in the rest of our
summit.
>> thank you, supervisor sutter
supervisors.
>> actually let's let's count
sorry, supervisor sheryl, I
think we should probably get to
our 230 special order.
>> do you need to call that or
I just go straight into it.
>> recognition of commendations
for meritorious service to the
city and county of san
francisco.
>> yes.
>> all right.
So we will start with district
11 supervisor chen.
Hi.
MAY I have yolanda come on,
come up.
I welcome colleagues and
friends today during women's
history month.
>> I'm so proud to offer
accommodation to our lovely,
inspiring and courageous
community leader from excelsior
district yolanda cruz.
>> please give her a round pass
.
Yolanda.
>> yolanda sorry.
It's a powerful testament to
the strength of women to the
power of community and to the
immigrant experience.
>> born in a small town in 1010
single mexico, yolanda grew up
in a community where
opportunity was a scarce.
But dreams were abandoned from
a young age.
Sue witnessed her parents
working tirelessly to care for
her three brothers and in suing
her the value of hard work and
resilience.
>> 20 years ago, yolanda make a
difficult decision to leave her
hometown and everything
familiar to come to san
francisco.
And here in district 11
excelsior she raised her four
children and make a home in the
district.
>> yolanda lives across the
street from cleveland
elementary, a place that has
been a second home to her over
the years.
It's a place where she
volunteers every day with other
parents mostly immigrant men
and women to share experiences
and resources, provide support
to each other and organize
together even though her
children and now her
grandchildren have long since
graduated from cleveland, she
continues to be part of this
school community as a fierce
advocate for educational equity
.
>> yolanda has been an active
member of community
organization that are champions
for immigrants, working class
and people of color including
coleman advocates for children
and youth and for their
speaking of her experiences
with this organization, sue
humbly shares that she has
learned so much and felt
incredibly supported.
>> and most importantly it
evolved.
It developed, it developed it
consciousness of how to defend
oneself and once community she
has been part of the marches
and mobilization that has
advocated for public school
students truly affordable
housing and for public bank out
of san francisco when she's not
organizing making tamales is
how being that this helping to
distribute food.
>> yolanda thinks that hopes
and dreams that she has for her
community that the next
generation coming up in the
neighborhood has the
opportunity to thrive and have
a better future that the
schools are not black, that our
children are not bullied
in school and that our teachers
and nurses are not getting laid
off and that they have strength
to cope with their share wave
after world on their shoulders.
>> yolanda proves that day
after day that this is the
woman who pop up for all
communities and that the
immigrant experiences it's
about extraordinary strength.
>> she's affectionately called
grandmother of the xhosa by the
children at cleveland
elementary school and I'm so
proud to honor yolanda today a
fashion we call donna ulis and
I invite you again to join me
in a round of applause and
congratulate her and thank her
calling us in between meals or
in the other until mystery
story that community is told.
When we were yourself I said
only low heel I want encanto to
inspire our evolution to lead
our community early three to
the excelsior yolanda chorus
the story of the yolanda simple
rosa testimonial ella first
let's play this in the la
comunidad l'expe
rience tell us
immigrants national park
in pueblo it's denouncing old
mexico yolanda crenshaw and
when I comunidad on the last
opportunity that is aranguiz
casals bitterness winners I
will end up on this record.
>> I will move back into boaz
by the rest our heroine can
supplement the paddock with as
was stress hermanos but I
include carlos los valores and
trabajo little ella resistencia
I seven S.A. Yolanda to more la
the official decision to the
sociedad natal it total or all
of ya para avenida san
francisco a creo cuatro rico's
propose a social order and only
three letters your yolanda have
you been to cleveland
elementary don't they a
oligarchy acido segundo I know
lago that lozano's is somewhere
on the terrace and pena como
voluntary at all osias control
paris and so my area on seem
quite as immigrants but
compartilhar experiencias have
a cautious apple you are said
mutu a mental organism segundos
episodic as was because our
race was nietos shangri la la
squalor.
Cleveland does it as a mature
tiempo ecac and operetta la
comunidad scholar commune
affirmative and so rather like
erratic educative yolanda I see
though integral to activa the
organization this communitarian
because on campus the los
immigrant is the classic
trabajo de las colonia as a
person as a color incluyendo
common advocates for children
and youth e there cuando abla
this experience has convinced
us already so soon this army
element the competition get up
and either mucho kisses seem to
increase element they are other
low mass importantly zika is a
concerns here the common
defenders say I see me my yes
or comunidad acito part the
marchers see mobilization this
yalla which other policies to
enter this quite as public as
liberian development as
actively chaperon bank banco
public san francisco condo and
restaurant in sandoval
community communitarian
sponsored to malaysia you are
at history will commit us
you'll end up in silence
esperanza seniors catnip
paraiso common era parochial
approximate congressional
scenario tangle oportunidad
prosper eat in the room for my
cannot see and intimidate us
and let us kill us because it
was my enfermedades no sanders
benito's getting a first a
parasitic frente el paso del
mundo sobre su sonorous yolanda
demonstra detras zia casillas
mukuru skin is stealing kidneys
so stealing most us comunidad
is equal experiential
immigrants this would not force
extraordinary is a cleveland
elementary like among carrying
your samantha love well I will
excelsior estoy mallorca also
the on yolanda we continue
samantha amara daniel elise he
lives in britain you say they
will not round of applause us
yes first I am ola yes I
yolanda and if they more
content aqui parking me
companion are right now me
grupo de mi grupo mayor the
donor but I will heal the iraqi
I abla landless jesse davis can
settlers tenemos and interrupt
me commonly down in latin in a
.
Hello my name is yolanda.
I am very happy to be here with
my colleagues and and with this
group is such a privilege for
me to come to you and to talk
about our needs.
Okay?
And locate your in me your list
all galaxies coalesce tenemos
this I see that this como and
pray tomada como stay my the
girls in my system they must
programs for our case the real
men they know say thank you
tano muturi la la la I so angel
e beirut I'm what I'm here for
is is because I wish for
schools or I have a dream for
schools because they need
nurses and they need teachers
and programs the programs are
being taken away right now and
that is my concern.
It's me in your ghetto to
monopolize pile of beverly
familia in less is square less
gay necessity well I come all
paris and milan place k kaigama
say that you I trust you that
if I would at go poor on our
own sueno americano kinesthetic
damo gabfest and restore by
sabathia no lost animals better
than battle your message at
least listen to content for but
if that aqui compartilhar la
necesidad this the todos etc.
Such as it can remove gay
catholic culture of mosque
another cannot ask you can look
at nosotros necesitamos para I
am here because I support
school parents and the
immigrant parents in san
francisco because most
immigrants came from many
places chasing the american
dream.
I'm very happy to be here
because I share the concerns
and the needs of our community
and I'm here to make sure that
we are heard and that you
listen to us.
>> my name
I want to thank you for the
commendation and I bless you
all of you from the bottom of
my heart.
>> and I want to thank you.
Okay
.
And next up we will have
district six supervisor matt
dorsey.
>> thank you PRESIDENT Mandl
men and preliminarily I want to
welcome the class from siv lev
how san francisco works and
express my gratitude to michael
adams for leading that effort.
Thank you all for your civic
engagement from the class and
just welcome you to san
francisco city hall.
>> but colleagues, the primary
reason I rise today is to honor
and to celebrate the remarkable
career of abby ent and to
recognize her extraordinary
contributions.
>> on the occasion of her
well-earned retirement, what
for the past seven years abby
has served as the executive
director of the san francisco
health service system leading
with a steady hand, a
compassionate heart and an
unwavering commitment to the
tens of thousands of members
who rely on it.
Her impact, however, extends
beyond these past seven years
with more than 35 years
in health care including eight
years at dignity health saint
francis memorial hospital and
12 years as an ems
administrator at the department
of public health.
Abby's career has been defined
by service leadership and an
unyielding drive to improve
health care access and
outcomes.
I've had the privilege of
serving on the health service
board for the past two years.
I can confidently say that abby
has been instrumental
in helping me not only navigate
the enormous complexities of
our health care system but also
to understand how the health
service service system works to
benefit its tens of thousands
of members.
Without her, frankly I'd still
be struggling to make sense of
acronyms and actuarial studies.
Abby has made sure that I and
the rest of this board are well
equipped with the knowledge we
need to be true assets to our
health care system and it is to
enable us to be responsible
stewards and for that we are
all deeply grateful.
>> one of the many things that
sets abby apart is her work
ethic and her leadership style
.
She is collaborative,
communicative and always
prioritizes members first.
She is fair, honest and
compassionate.
Values that have been at the
core of everything she has
accomplished.
She has not only embraced the
transformation in the health
care industry but has worked
tirelessly to address its
rising costs to ensure equity
in access to care and to foster
community partnerships to
maximize resources.
Abby's ability to lead with
vision and pragmatism has
helped snf access be at the
forefront of member and health
services and well-being.
As executive director, her
champion ship for data driven
decision making make possible
innovative solutions that
improve the health of our
city's workforce and its
retirees.
Whether leading the transition
back from a post-covid work
environment advocating for high
quality and sustainable health
care benefits or leading
sometimes tough negotiations
with vendors, stakeholders and
our health service system
board, she has led with
integrity and purpose every
step of the way.
Beyond abby's professional
accomplishments, she really is
an exceptional person as she
steps into retirement.
I know she is looking forward
to spending more time with her
husband larry and her two young
adult sons.
Living in picturesque sonoma
she is ready to embrace a new
chapter filled with family
friends and if I had to guess
probably some well-deserved
relaxation.
Fortunately I am reliably
informed that abby is well
aware that her retirement will
not relieve her of the
obligation to take my calls as
an unpaid member of my brain
trust on the intricacies of
health care policy and
benefits.
Abby on behalf of the city and
county of san francisco, the
health service board and the
tens of thousands of city
employees and retirees whose
lives and health you have
inestimable improved thank you.
Congratulations on her
retirement you have more than
earned and I invite you to say
a few words.
>> but first connie chan thank
you PRESIDENT Domain.
>> I just I want to add to and
concur.
Supervisor dorsey's sentiment
and express to you director ns
I am grateful as well I.
I think that director abby ns
is one of the quietest.
If we if san francisco is a
basketball team I would say you
know director yance is one of
the quickest, quietest, most
valuable players on this team.
You you have played a
tremendous role and critical
role to really the health and
well-being of the city workers
both active and retired.
And when I became I was a
rookie supervisor and joined
the health service board.
I had no idea what I was
getting myself into truly those
meeting and I love city and
love all the readings and
documents and yet it was very
difficult and it was probably
easier to watch paint dry than
go through the service board
hearings warning to new
colleagues but it was the most
well worth of my time I think
really in city you actually
took that time to learn about
health care system to really
learn from you.
Director yeah and about how
this actually work and is
really complex work and it's a
thankless job and I'm just so
grateful that you were there
for us and I'm so actually sad
to see you retire.
>> well deserved retirement and
yet it's a very difficult time
for the health care system not
just for san francisco but
really for the country as well.
And and I really hope that we
could continue to call on you
for your advice because it is a
difficult time that we must
maneuver at this moment.
But for all that you have done
for us, I'm just so grateful
and thank you.
>> thank you supervisor chan I
also got to do a little tour of
duty on the health service
board and very much echo the
comments of my colleagues.
We are lucky as a city to have
had abby and taken care of us
so thank you.
And now I think supervisor
dorsey would like to invite you
to say a few words.
>> well thank you very much for
the accolades.
It's been up quite a wild ride.
I entered the arena seven years
ago and thought it thinking I
knew a lot about health care
and I had a lot more to learn
and we are at a time of great
change in the health care
system and consolidation and
increase in pricing and so it
is a time to be very rigorous
about our work that we do
in providing those health care
services for all of the active
and retired employees from the
city as well as the school
district and community college
and the court.
So we have pretty broad
constituency I have to say that
I could not do it without my
leadership team who has just
risen to every occasion.
I do not shy away from
challenging assignments and I
pass them on to my team and
they often are a little bit
surprised about the expectation
but they always meet or exceed
.
So I really am very grateful to
all of them.
I've had the honor to develop
two strategic plans for the
organization and we're about to
embark on on the next one.
But they've I think have been
spot on to help our guiding
light where our emphasis has
been around equity
affordability, advancing the
practice of primary care,
providing adequate mental
health services and running an
efficient operation and at hcc
and I think we've made major
head roads into all of these
areas and they will need
continued guidance to get us
there and serving and in being
sure that we have our role
in transforming health care
systems and it's often not
clear what it is and even as a
purchaser with as much money as
we spend on health care, it is
often not heard.
So I think we need to continue
to be sure that we have
influence over those health
care systems and the rising
cost.
And then just to touch on we
were I was pleased to be able
to lead the agency through the
pandemic to ensure that our
members had access to covid
vaccine.
It was great to be a part of
that incredible team here
in san francisco that had such
remarkable results from
preventing the spread and death
of many from the vaccine.
So it was a joy to be part of
that.
I did share with folks that I
found a letter that was written
to my grandmother in 1918 who
was being thanked for her
service during the pandemic.
At that time I thought that was
a crazy that I was carrying on
that tradition and and it's
true that the collaboration and
communication is key to this
job.
There's just so many
complexities and we can't do
it.
None of us can do it alone.
So I do appreciate the support
that the board of supervisors
has provided myself in our
organization over the years.
It's made a difference.
I know I speak to many people,
many of our members over time
and they're not shy to call me
when they want to lift so and
that's how I have to but it's
been a it's been a real honor
and a pleasure to serve the
city of san francisco.
So thank you so much.
Director, why don't you come
into the well for a photograph
with the board so close the box
is too big to see to give you
.
last but not least from
district eight I want to invite
nelson barry and the urban
angels to come up today.
It is my honor to present a
special commendation to nelson
barry and the urban angels, an
organization he founded
initially to help unhoused
people but which has since
expanded its reach to support
low income families and
children across san francisco.
>> the urban angels have become
a durable strand in the city's
safety net.
What began as a food and
clothing giveaway group has
evolved to offer school
backpack computer aided home
tutoring for early elementary
students and bilingual
counseling services.
>> urban angels began ten years
ago as a breakfast group in a
diamond heights restaurant.
Nelson barry then a retired
lawyer, was discouraged by the
long rows of tarps and tents
along division street and
wanted to help.
The group started by
distributing burritos.
Next came socks, clothing and
more food.
Barry's small flock of helpers
expanded as word spread within
months volunteers were hitting
sidewalks in the tenderloin and
mission districts.
Nelson plugged into other
nonprofits and groups such as
urban alchemy code tenderloin
and the homeless prenatal
program to match needs with
resources.
The angels set up a sidewalk
set up sidewalk tables outside
drop in centers and teamed up
with neighborhood groups.
by 2024 the urban angels had
given away some 12,000 clothing
bags for men, women and
children.
When covid hit, the urban
angels stepped up.
They distributed hand sanitizer
and face masks when facemasks
when the public supply ran
short two years ago, barry and
the urban angels decided to try
a new direction helping young
children keep up with
schoolwork.
The angels took on tutoring
developing a program that gives
students laptop ppes and
matches them with trained
instructors who measure their
progress.
The effort supported students
still struggling after covid
related school closures.
Marcia contreras, deputy
executive director of mission
housing development corp., said
of nelson.
He's very thoughtful, creative
and action driven.
We could not have asked for a
better community partner.
The angels now offer a spectrum
of programs related to
nutrition schoolwork and social
activities including trips and
art classes.
>> thank you nelson barry and
the urban angels for all you've
done and will continue to do to
make our city safer and
healthier and to support the
next generation of san
franciscans.
And with that the floor is
yours.
MR. PRESIDENT, members of the
board, all my volunteers and
other guests in the room.
As you heard, my name is nelson
barry.
i'm PRESIDENT And founder of
urban angels S.F. And it's an
honor to speak for you today on
behalf of our organization.
I first I'd like to express our
immense gratitude for receiving
this commendation for our work
supporting san francisco's
unhoused and low income
communities over the past
decade to be recognized by a
board that is deeply committed
to fostering positive change
in our city is truly humbling.
I want to extend a special and
heartfelt thanks to you
PRESIDENT Madeline your belief
in urban angels S.F. And your
continued support have been
invaluable.
Your guidance and encouragement
have been a source of
inspiration for us and have
helped us propel our mission
forward.
It's leaders like you who
enable us to carry our work
with renewed energy and
dedication.
For the past ten years urban
angels S.F. Has been focused on
distributing essential
supplies, clothing, food, water
and the like to those in need
striving to provide not only
sustenance but dignity.
But today as we look to the
future we are excited to
announce an expanded mission to
empower the education of
unhoused children in grades two
through six.
This new initiative is named at
bridging the education gap for
these children who face the
most significant barriers to
success through high impact
tutoring in reading and math.
Our book lending program and
our parent mentoring
initiatives we are committing
to providing a holistic
approach to education.
This year we will host our
seventh annual program where
1000 unhoused children and
others from families living at
the poverty level will receive
brand new high quality
backpacks filled with new
school supplies ensuring that
they have the resources they
need to start their school year
with hope, confidence and
readiness.
These programs are about much
more than academic achievement
.
They are about building a
stable and joyful future for
these children.
As you know, education is the
key to breaking the cycle of
poverty.
And through these efforts we
aim to give these children the
tools, encouragement and
support to rise to reach their
full potential.
In closing, I want to once
again express I was I wish to
once again express our deepest
gratitude to the entire board
of supervisors, especially
PRESIDENT Randleman for your
support today.
Your recognition strengthens
the vital partnership between
city leaders like yourselves
and community based
organizations like ours.
Together we can continue to
uplift the most vulnerable
members of our community and
create a more inclusive,
compassionate san francisco.
Thank you for your continued
support of our partnership as
we work together to build a
brighter future for all.
>> and if I if I MAY, I'd like
to introduce some of the people
behind me very quickly.
Jason patel is one of our
longest standing board members
and she represents six other
women who are on our board.
Two are chinese to or from
india.
>> one is mexican and indian
one sri lankan.
We also have an advisory board
with two gay members and a
member from the hispanic
committee.
>> in the back, marsha
contreras and gina rodriguez
are from mission housing
development corporation which
is a they operate several
residences in the city where
the families and the children
that we serve live.
And so thank you for coming
today.
Everybody else here is part of
our volunteer corps.
And as you can see,
volunteerism is driven by women
.
We have seven women on our
board.
I think they scared off all the
men but they stood up and they
do the work.
And we have all of these women
here except for me and al.
And we're proud to be among
this group who really drive the
passion and the energy and the
mission in our group.
And we have one special note I
want to make to karen andrea,
laura and maria teresa here.
The small family lives in the
tenderloin and they have showed
up every thursday morning at
our office for the last five
years to sort hundreds of bags
of clothing that there's none
prepared for distribution the
next week to the prenatal
clinic and to numerous other
organizations such as code
tenderloin, urban alchemy.
And without them we couldn't
get this program moving.
>> and I just like to give them
and all the other volunteers a
big round of applause.
>> thank you, rafael, for
letting me do that.
Okay.
On over here.
This is the payoff because
that's a photo of me.
>> but you want to give it to
me?
Yeah.
You're doing all right.
Thank you.
All right.
>> thank you, everybody.
We're retreating to max's opera
plaza for a little reception.
Any of you who want to put your
aids in charge here and join
us?
I understand they make a wicked
martini.
>> thank you again.
All right.
And I believe that concludes
our commendations and we can go
back to rollcall.
>> next up to introduce new
business is supervisor sherril
summit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor walton.
>> thank you so much, MADAM
Clerk.
Colleagues last year we took an
important step by passing
amendments to the city's
language access ordinance
through a collaborative process
between the office of community
engagement and immigrant
affairs, oca and the community
today along with supervisors
chan fielder and chen.
>> we are calling for a hearing
to assess the progress of the
implementation of the lio and
ensure our commitments are
being met.
As part of this discussion.
We will also review the 2025
language access compliance
summary report provided
annually by the office of
community engagement and
immigrant affairs.
The upcoming budget and
legislative and now analysts
report on language access which
I requested on JULY 9th, 2024
and is currently being
finalized and hear directly
from the community about their
experience and concerns
regarding the city's language
access services.
We are lucky to live in a city
as diverse as san francisco
where our communities speak a
wide range of languages
ensuring language access is
critical to making sure all
residents regardless of the
language they speak can fully
engage with and benefit from
city services and participate
in a democratic process.
I look forward to a productive
discussion as we continue
working toward a more
inclusive, accessible and
equitable san francisco for all
the rest of us.
>> thank you.
Supervisor walton.
Supervisor chan.
Submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor chen submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor dorsey.
thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues, I would ask that we
conclude today's board meeting
with an in memoriam for the
late alisha miele who is the
father of mosher miele, a
veteran deputy city attorney
and a friend of colleague and
colleague of mine and a
longtime community leader.
Alijah miele was born in jordan
in 1932.
He immigrated to san francisco
in 1966 in pursuit of the
american dream a dream he would
fulfill with hard work,
resilience and boundless love
for his adopted country and his
family.
Prior to immigrating to the
united states, he was a skilled
carpenter even contributing to
the production of lawrence of
arabia part of a production
design team that would go on to
win the 1963 oscar for best art
direction and set design which
was one of seven oscars that
film won that year including
best picture.
Here in san francisco, ali
worked as a busser at original
joe's on taylor street and
became a proud member of the
carpenters union.
He later moved to los angeles
where he met the love of his
life antoinette jameel and
built a successful small
business the monte carlo
limousine.
He was beloved by his clients
including boxing legend
muhammad ali who famously
insisted on sitting up front to
swap stories with him.
Ali eventually retired back
in the bay area living in the
salvation army silvercrest
apartments in south of market
and also in willow grill at
glen in san jose.
He was a devoted husband,
father and grandfather survived
by the love of his life and his
partner antoinette and his son
mo and grandchildren oliver and
kate.
Our hearts go out to them and
to all who join us and all are
in honoring ali's legacy a
well-lived life rooted in hard
work, community and family.
MAY he rest in peace and the
rest I submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor dorsey supervisor
and gaudio submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor fielder.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I have found
it imperative to introduce a
resolution addressing the
increasing crisis of family
homelessness and the harm on
children from the reinstated 90
day shelter.
>> length of stay policy.
For the past few weeks I've
heard more and more stories
from families with looming
eviction dates at their
shelters who are fearful and
stress about the threat of
eviction and being returned to
the streets.
>> we we've been told by two
sage and the mayor's office
that this policy is to better
address the needs of families
in our community and to ensure
families are making quote
positive progress on their
families success plans.
>> however, the actual
implementation of this policy
has been a nightmare for
families and fails to solve for
larger barriers that are
actually in the way of families
making positive progress.
The policy has escalated to the
point that just yesterday two
families were facing 5 P.M.
Evictions with the threat of
the shelter provider calling as
of today to remove them.
I repeat a shelter provider
threatened to call police on
families at a shelter.
>> it turns out that the
families were waiting for
scheduled appointments for
housing referrals something
that should have been
considered positive progress.
>> agency overturned the
provider's removal decision and
the families received 30 day
extensions which is a relief
but is only going to bring us
back to square one in APRIL.
>> these are not anomalies as
of this policy rollout I've
heard from as of used social
workers, medical professionals
and community organizations.
Dozens of stories of confusion
and fear.
>> and this reinstated policy
in its current implementation
and is ineffective as it is
callous.
I outlined in an extensive memo
last week the implementation
issues in this shelter state
policy such as families not
being informed of their ability
to request an extension.
The incredible discretion
providers and case managers
have in dictating what positive
progress means let alone the
larger systemic barriers that
families have in accessing
housing and exiting the shelter
system.
>> even hsa and shelter
providers have acknowledged
those barriers.
Also most families are not
being informed of their right
to submit a grievance should an
extension be denied which is a
violation of city policy.
>> I sent this memo to the
mayor's policy chief and hsa
and they have been open to
working on solutions.
I'm now formally calling on the
mayor and agency to rescind or
drastically reform the 90 day
shelter, stay policy and work
with the board of supervisors
and stakeholders to develop a
policy that avoids placing
undue stress on families.
These reforms should include
increases in shelter and
housing options to address
family homelessness.
>> this policy is partially
predicated on the notion that
families refusing to leave
shelters are the problem.
>> there has been no readily
available data to suggest this
.
No parent wishes to raise their
children in a shelter.
These shelters are a last
resort for families.
This policy is not working and
rather than committing
substantial jail time in all of
the different branches of
litigating family cases one by
one we need a better policy.
>> the stories we are hearing
are heart wrenching and I
literally cannot sleep at
night.
>> knowing families with
children of all ages are being
subject to this policy with
inconsistency and callousness.
>> no child should have to live
on the streets and the city
shouldn't be the cause for any
child being back on the streets
.
As the policy currently stands
,we need to do better.
>> we can end family
homelessness in san francisco
and we should be working
together to make it happen.
>> thank you.
Supervisors chen melgar and
walton for your early
co-sponsorship and partnership
.
>> I hope all of you will join
us in supporting san
francisco's most vulnerable
children and working to find
real lasting solutions to
family homelessness.
The rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor fielder.
Supervisor mohamud submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor gentleman thank you,
MADAM Clerk.
I have one in memoriam today.
I'm asking that we adjourn our
meeting in memory of alan
jacobs, our city's former
planning director and a
district eight resident who
passed away on FEBRUARY 18th at
the age of 96.
Alan was born on DECEMBER 29th,
1928.
He grew up in cleveland, ohio
and earned a bachelor of
architecture degree from miami
university.
He studied at the graduate
school of design at harvard
university and earned a
master's degree in city
planning from the university of
pennsylvania from 1954 to 1955.
He was a fulbright scholar
in city planning at university
college in london.
He began his career as an urban
planner at the pittsburgh
regional planning association
where he worked for seven years
before moving to india to
advise on a metropolitan plan
for calcutta.
He continued to practice urban
design throughout his life and
throughout the world working on
projects in san francisco,
berkeley, los angeles,
portland, vancouver, critica
in brazil and other cities.
During his tenure as our
director of city planning from
1967 to 1975, alan was
responsible for developing
major elements of the city's
comprehensive plan as well as
design guidelines for downtown
development.
He also focused on revitalizing
neighborhoods throughout san
francisco to make them more
livable.
>> most notably, alan was
charged with creating an urban
design plan for the city.
The plan was innovative in its
approach and presentation
popular among residents and
widely heralded across the
professional community.
It identified key principles of
the city's urban form and
patterns based on a series of
detailed studies and
illustrated these with
hand-drawn images that made the
ideas accessible.
Alan joined the faculty of the
uc berkeley department of city
and regional planning in 1975,
serving two terms as department
chair before retiring in 2001.
He established the department's
urban design concentration and
helped found the college's
master of urban design program.
He was a prolific writer.
he authored several books
including making city planning
work published in 1980 which
chronicled his years as san
francisco's planning director
looking at cities published
in 1985 great streets published
in 1993 and the boulevard book
history evolution design of
multi-way boulevards which he
coauthored with his wife
elizabeth mcdonald and yoda and
rafi rafi published in 2003 and
the good city reflections and
imaginations published in 2011.
Great streets is the best known
of these and is still in print
to this day through text
freehand sketches plans and
sections, the book reveals
alan's persistent curiosity
about how city streets work and
social spaces.
It also pyle pioneered his
square mile up or square mile
map methodology which has since
become a standard way for urban
designers and city planners to
analyze the urban form and
fabric of cities in a
comparative way.
>> the book is filled with
alan's close observations his
passionate, passionate joy for
cities and his love of life.
There is a magic to great
streets, he writes.
We are attracted to them not
because we have to go there but
because we want to be there.
The best star is joyful as they
are utilitarian they are
entertaining and they're open
to all.
They permit anonymity at the
same time as individual
recognition.
They are symbols of a community
and its history.
They represent a public memory.
they are places for escape and
for romance places to act and
to dream.
>> I knew of alan jacobs long
before I was elected and it was
my great honor to be his
supervisor.
Alan is survived by his wife
elizabeth, two daughters, a
son, seven grandchildren.
And countless friends and fans
.
Thank you alan for your service
to sam san francisco and for
inspiring generations of urban
planners.
MAY your memory be a blessing?
And the rest I submit.
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT and
MR. PRESIDENT seeing no names
on the roster that concludes
the introduction of new
business.
>> all right.
Then let's go to public
comment.
>> okay.
At this time the board welcomes
general public comment as the
public members are lining up on
their right hand side of the
chamber.
As I stated earlier, we will
first hear remote general
public comment from an
individual vetted pursuant to
the americans with disabilities
act.
I'll ask my staff now to please
bring that caller into this
meeting for two minutes.
>> welcome color.
>> hello.
This is michael cottrell is
calling in to make public
comment.
I am very concerned about the
safety issues in the castro
district.
Recently a homeless neighbor
named dale passed away.
He died on a cold sidewalk and
we saw a publicity stunt by
elected officials in response.
I related to safety concerns on
sunday evening at about 8 P.M.
A gay man was viciously
attacked under the castro
theater marquee and his blood
was left on the sidewalk under
the castro theater marquee.
>> the intensive tail and the
attack on the gay man on sunday
night are causing many, many
concerns in the castro.
>> unfortunately we are not
hearing from our elected
officials regarding our demand
.
>> our demand is for an urgent
town hall meeting this week
with our elected officials to
listen to us.
We want a public comment time
as long as it takes to hear
from everyone in the castro.
>> at a town hall meeting with
our elected officials, we all
know the gop fear is holding
town halls because they don't
want to hear criticism.
Unfortunately we in the castro
district we see that same
attitude of fear by the elected
officials who have not
announced a town hall meeting
or in memoriam for dale.
And because of the vicious
attack on sunday night at the
castro theater, we want a town
hall meeting on safety issues
this week.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> we will now move to those
folks in the room.
>> welcome to our first speaker
.
>> grow food since you didn't
introduce anything but a
script.
I mean reading a script stupid
script including watch out on
because using a child children
homelessness for to develop
trafficking is not going to
work well with me at all.
>> so since you didn't
introduce anything concerning
the measure problem we have
which is whether manipulation,
food poisoning which concerns
every single one of us I'm
introducing now I told you last
week you have to do it now I'm
introducing a sort of call to
disobey disregard anything that
this current is telling you to
do.
This includes being tax
everything until they address
this problem of weather
manipulation that is messing
with our skies.
>> now everybody disobey that
includes traffic lights.
No now you do that with what
the this fake doesn't want to
do response ability and
critical thinking if you need
to take a right turn when you
want you look it safe I'm going
it that's available civil
disobedience this is fake and
criminal does it now your
system you started the reason
why you strategy of GOD I
thought GOD does and what is
because it comes from your
unintelligent ugliness see so
it's going to fill I see
everything don't mess with our
food and it's mom and that's of
course right the engineer
mosquitoes to attack us now to
protect the so called belts are
you choking?
That's a revolution.
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> welcome, MISS Chandler.
Thank you.
Appreciate it.
My name is soliloquy a chandler
and my son was murdered jelani
jama one day JANUARY the 9th
2015 the san francisco
quadruple homicide which it
took ten years for me to
finally get a trial date
SEPTEMBER 18th in MAY trial
2024 SEPTEMBER 28th I ended up
having a stroke unfortunately
being hospitalized for two
weeks.
But that's not the real concern
that I want to talk about
today.
I'm very, very discouraged as I
look into the chamber and I
notice that maybe 1 or 2
commonly called
african-american children we
known as the hebrew nation
that's one of the discussions
that's being discussed all over
the world.
We're nowhere in the chambers
because the bottom line is I
see the beauty of all the
cultures coming together and
talking about their their
victories.
But we have to understand that
when you destroy a nation and
you take their language
in their communication and
their sacred rites and their
relationships with their gods
and give them external you have
nothing and I'm request thing
that we begin to have a serious
dialog concerning what we need
to do concerning the raising of
my people back into the status
of who they were originally
before their language and their
culture and the enslavement
took place.
My people are dying and I'm
very concerned and what I see
is that within the political
realm I don't think we are
addressing it.
I don't have to explain I'm not
a racist person but I realize
that even the city of san
francisco is a representation
of a sanctus.
I think you call it a sanctuary
city but nothing is really
being done for the history of
who we are in building this
country.
>> we're not addressing this
issue and I think that we
really thank you, MR. Quere
chandler for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker.
Well, good afternoon.
I'm lisa platt, a d2 resident.
I'm going to start with just
the facts.
>> the us has had a shortage of
that lately so maybe this will
be a little refreshing to us
all.
>> you all passed a resolution
ensuring public transit remains
convenient and for that I
personally thank you and we
have a near term S.F. Mta
budget shortfall primarily
caused by reduced parking
revenues in downtown garages as
mta has found every bit of
savings they possibly could
reducing the 2025 gap to just
15 million that 15 million can
be found one of three ways one
cut muni service causing an
already kneecaps system to be
transfer dependent increasing
the time to travel by ten plus
minutes at a time when as the
mayor wants more businesses are
doing return to office to find
new sources of parking revenue
like running meters in the
evening just like they do
in cities like austin, boston
and chicago three to a small
general fund transfer or have
sfm to use a bit of reserves
number one has a major impact
on tourism property values and
economic recovery one and two
have potential political
collateral damage if you cut
the service of the large
majority of san franciscans who
use transit, they're not going
to help you get the funding you
need in 2026 efforts you would
have already broken promises to
your constituents if you add
parking hours a small but large
amount of people MAY sound
shutdown but they were unlikely
to support an mta 2026 funding
effort anyway.
>> number three is the easiest
it buys us time to get funding
in place in 2026 and leaves no
political wake.
Pick your poison but please be
strategic.
>> making summer muni cuts is
economic, public trust and
political suicide.
>> please choose parking or
reserves to put some action
behind.
Thank you for your comments.
Let's welcome our next speaker
.
>> well we gave it abby award
combination and I'm reading
their mass recommended but not
required for all and it's just
all lies and B.S. And you know
,it's really sad that nobody's
talking about how covid it was
when the cdc put snake venom
in all the water systems and
got a sick that's how it
happened.
It really did.
>> and richard, DR. Richard
bartlett who is curing like a
thousand patients per month
100% of the time using what's
called monoclonal antibodies.
>> you know what that is?
That's antivenom.
It's ants.
>> look up this guy named DR.
Brian artist brilliant guy.
I mean he discovered this when
his friend richard bartlett
sent him a text.
You know, if you got bit by a
snake, would you go to the E.R.
And you know, get the antidote?
That's all he said and it got
him researching and then it
came to him you know, covid
with snake a synthetic snake
venom put into the water
systems by the cdc from JANUARY
of 2020.
Now in OCTOBER of 2020 a random
reporter this is a providence
of GOD look 52 seconds well
help lord to type in the DR.
Artists show A.R. Diaz and
scroll down to the antidote.
>> okay.
This guy is amazing.
He he's the guy who found out
that when fauci and deborah
burks, you know, recommended
the what's it called remdesivir
it was it would kill the
patient in nine nine days
straight and he studied the
studies that fauci recommended
for how great you know,
remdesivir is and he found out
it's deadly poison.
You know everything the health
department were giving him
awards, you know, please come
on now that you must know these
things I'm not smarter than
everybody.
>> I'm just a carpet cleaner.
You should know these things.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker.
hello, board griffin leisure
due to resident hope I have all
of your attention here are not
sure if I can talk on something
and in the past from this
agenda but regarding the
vacancy tax I think the
majority of that board is is
pro housing and wants more
housing built here in san
francisco.
I will confidently say that
landlords developers will not
be incentivized if a vacancy
tax does pass.
>> I'm I'm going to continue to
advocate on something with that
behalf.
>> I'm pausing your time just
for a moment.
Are you talking about an item
on our agenda?
Could it be item 11?
Item 14 it wouldn't be possible
for you to that item went
through committee and already
had its public comment
fulfilled.
>> got it.
I also have something an
upcoming agenda.
I'll start your time again.
Here we go.
Okay.
You have a minute and 34
seconds left.
>> thank you.
Regarding the distribution and
fairness act regarding I think
that supervisors souder feel
fielder melgar and walton are
proposing on the agenda coming
up regarding h s h to explore
for and implement a fair
distribution I would take a
step back and think about what
the cost would be to implement
bill the shelters that we need
in the city versus using
ideology to think about or and
to propose the distribution of
homeless throughout the city.
For example soma has I think I
read 26% of homeless population
.
>> soma should be then
responsible for that 26% it
shouldn't have to live and move
into different different
neighborhoods that are already
doing their part potentially on
you think about the cost right
now h s h has an $846 million
budget and on average each
homeless cost is $101,000 based
off of the last point in time
count in JANUARY 2024.
I urge you to think about the
cost before just wreaking havoc
on other communities neighbors
,neighborhoods.
>> thank you for your comments.
Oh good afternoon.
My name is jaime viloria I am
tenderloin resident and also
part of the muni now muni
forever campaign.
Thank you for passing
resolution supporting muni and
thank you to all the
supervisors here who continue
to be open and having
discussions with our campaign.
The resolutions are great but
we need actions and we need it
this year and we need it
locally.
Over the past three years
transit advocates have been
sounding the alarm of the
impending deficit.
We helped in getting a state
bailout two years ago but
nothing has been done to
address the deficit.
Last year advocates put a truly
grassroots ballot measure to
raise 25 millions for transit.
It passed but was invalidated
by a word imposed from prop em.
>> now all we've heard from our
leaders to address this deficit
is we're advocating the state
are waiting for a regional
measure.
Those are the same things we
heard in the past three years.
We still don't have funding and
no plan six express accepted to
risk it on the uncertainty let
us not go there again.
Let's take steps locally this
year the optics of a very
wealthy city where about seven
out of 11 supervisors have
assets over a million and the
mayor inheriting $1 billion
fortune while allowing cuts and
punting the potential solutions
somewhere else does not leave
me with a lot of confidence or
feel inspired we can make our
city shine.
With the backdrop of federal
cuts orchestrated by the
wealthy, we need to be san
franciscans and find solutions
locally and show that we really
are innovative and progressive.
Stop the cuts, do something
this year and work with us
advocates who are ready to
mobilize to find solutions and
make it happen.
Money is love.
Let us not fail it.
>> thank you for your time.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome to our next speaker.
>> hello supervisors.
My name is avril.
You are a resident of district
one.
I also want to thank you for
passing the resolution to
support muni in your last
meeting.
>> I'm here because I want to
urge this board to support a
general fund transfer to the
sfm to or at least work with
the S.F. Mta to help prevent
this year's summer cuts.
>> if you're there last week
in the S.F. Mta board meeting
so many people showed up asking
for sfm to not to cut low
income toe subsidies not to cut
crossing guards, not to cut
muni lines at hundreds of
thousands of people use every
single day.
This is what is at risk this
summer if we do not do
anything.
This could potentially all go
away as if mta and the
advocates have been working
tirelessly to prevent these
cuts.
We need the support of this
board and the mayor to have the
political will to make things
happen.
It is unlikely that a regional
measure will fully fund muni
and if our city cannot
administer the self-help it
needs to help save our own
transportation system.
What will the other counties
think?
Do you think they're willing to
tax themselves to support a
city that can't help
themselves?
Now is the time to address this
deficit when it is still
manageable.
Please work with S.F. Mta on
general fund transfer to save
muni this summer.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Nobody wants closed terry.
>> terry, you're out of order
when you do that.
>> hello.
My name is liam mckeever.
I am sharing my perspective as
a trans latin x homeowner in d
six.
>> I believe a lot of you know
this person, J.J. Smith.
>> he seems to be a nice guy
who's interested in helping
people.
I wish that's how I knew him.
Unfortunately it is not.
>> it's also wearing a hat
saying that says matt dorsey.
>> a couple weeks ago J.J.
Smith recorded homeless people
and myself at a rally in the
tenderloin and tom wolf
commented on that ex post that
said lol get em jj.
>> I took that as encouragement
of jay's behavior.
>> jj left a comment on my
substack.
I write about the.
I took that as he is also
observing me write about the
there as well.
>> two weeks ago you MAY
remember that he recorded me
in this chamber.
>> posted it immediately on x
which riled up transphobic
hate.
He called me.
He she it's this is an email
saying you put my life at risk
and I point out exactly what he
did.
>> this is my supervisor
talking about tom wolfe, his
recovery drug advisor saying
never be silenced.
Tom wolfe the moral high ground
is yours.
Keep fighting.
Tom wolfe was also harassing me
at this time so I took that as
encouragement to my supervisor
to for tom wolfe to continue my
harassment and now I have
people online that I do not
know who seem to know my
supervisor and jj sharing
things about my restraining
order information and other
things on how to defeat me and
thus continue harassing me.
I don't know why they are so
invested in harassing me.
I wish some of you would ask
questions about what is this
going what's going on?
>> what's the connection?
>> must live.
Transpeople must live.
I have a copy for the record.
Thank you.
Thank you liam mckeever for
your comments.
We'll come and collect that
from you.
>> welcome to the next speaker.
Please.
>> my name is and I'm dave
sherman.
I'm speaking on the behalf of
purchase checks millennial
holders.
It is not san francisco.
It is a brutal city.
Specifically targeted us with
the rideshare.
City destroyed everything and
devastated our life.
We are not stupid.
We understand everything.
City extorted our money to
accommodate elderly wheelchairs
and disabled people's due
concern about a wheelchair
disabled elderly people.
But you are not concerned about
our loans.
It is a cause of the poor taxi
driver to the city.
>> that's why cities are
recovering.
Believe me next 12 years city
will not recover if you don't
bail us out.
If new york city can lower the
price on medallion, why central
city cannot.
>> this is the time to do it.
>> reduce the price to
$125,000.
>> thank you for your comments
.
Welcome to the next speaker.
Good afternoon.
My name is ali oscar.
Medallion one, 225.
Same reason we keep coming for
years and I don't know why are
we not provided this justice
for the last 1213 years.
We're becoming so I think the
city is falling apart every
department of the city is
falling apart I guess is the
karma if you're not going to
get together and provide the
justice to equally to everybody
who deserves to have the
justice then I don't think so.
You will recover no matter what
you do.
So I think you should think
again and see because the karma
I told you like before pandemic
the karma is going to give and
give and he got it so please
get together honestly
positively.
>> try to cover every issue we
have in the city just justice.
Believe me if you start
providing the justice the lord
is going to provide that drive
to this city.
>> this city is going to become
the same city it was 20 years
ago.
>> so please thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to the next speaker
.
Yeah I am one of the cab driver
who wrongfully by by the of the
funding of city of san
francisco but by abusing of the
mta so I believe you have a
yeah some kind of a solution
but you don't want to edit and
you are you know there you are
responsible but you don't want
to do that I don't know why you
are pushing out all these cab
driver who bought a medallion
to be street of san francisco
join with the homeless people.
That's what I going to be we
what we going to be happen
pretty soon so that I also
support my fellow cabbies that
as a come I always goes around
comes around sort of why we
collab this series because of
you that you are doing that did
take a detailed opportunity of
any poor people live in people
that you already make that
wrongfully decision and you
know no pay to pay to walk
in this cities is no good you
know it's always goes around
comes around thank you thank
you for your comments before
the next speaker begins if you
are here to provide the board
general public comment we'd
appreciate it if you would step
over to your right hand side
near the curtains otherwise MR.
Duffy will be our last speaker.
>> yes.
My name is MR. Duffy.
I'm I too am a member of a
bizarre subculture group and
mayor I'm glad I don't have to
be the one that divvies up the
money.
>> you know, I understand
there's a limited amount and
you got to make choices but I
think MR. Is MR. Hyman's
rationale was pretty good and
of how hard they're trying to
get money and that they're just
$15 million short you know I'm
I'm surprised at how often I am
am using the service now as i
get older you know I just say a
couple other things.
Yes.
Antivenom is in fact an
antibody and it would be nice
if some you know, if someone's
worried about things that are
in the water, you know, if they
were looking like heavy metals
and organic poly chloride as
you know things that are
actually in the water that
would be nice.
>> thank you for your comments,
MR. PRESIDENT.
All right.
>> public comment is now closed
.
>> MADAM Clerk.
Let's go to our first adoption
without committee reference
agenda items 25 through 29 yes
items 25 through 29 were
introduced for adoption but
without committee reference a
unanimous vote is required for
adoption of a resolution on
first reading today.
Alternatively, a member MAY
require a resolution on first
reading to go to committee.
>> I don't see anyone severing
any items so MADAM Clerk can
you please call the roll on
these items on items 25 through
29.
Supervisor melgar melgar eyes
supervisor sadr.
Sadr eyes supervisor sherril
sherril eyes supervisor walton
walton eyes supervisor chin
chin eyes supervisor chin chin
eyes supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio and
engardio I supervisor fielder
fielder I supervisor mahmood
mahmood I and supervisor
randleman hi management either
ari lebanese without objection
the resolutions are adopted
madam clerk do we have any
imperative agenda items?
>> I have none to report MR.
PRESIDENT.
>> then could you please read
the in memoriam?
>> yes.
Today's meeting will be
adjourned in memory of the
following beloved individuals
on behalf of supervisor dorsey
for the late MR. Ali jamil on
behalf of board PRESIDENT
Mandel man for professor
emeritus at the college of
environmental design at
berkeley and former planning
director MR. Alan jacobs.
>> and I believe that brings us
to the end of our agenda, MADAM
Clerk is there any further
business before us today that
concludes our business for
today.
>> thank you.
As there's no further business